<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Pages on Burak Sina Akbudak</title>
        <link>http://localhost:1313/en/page/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Pages on Burak Sina Akbudak</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-US</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/en/page/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
            <title>About</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/en/page/about/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/page/about/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;My full name is Burak Sina Akbudak, though I prefer to be called just Sina. I have, and probably will at the end of my undergrad years, worked on many fields such as formal mathematics with LLMs, music generation/musical information retrieval, computer graphics and heck, even finite state automaton. I speak Turkish native and English at professional level. I&amp;rsquo;m currently a undergrad at Bogazici University, Computer Engineering Department.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My main aim during the undergraduate years is to see and understand as much as I can so that when I graduate I can have many directions to go for. Although there are many fields that I am passionate to work on, I am in the search for the one that my skills and interest aligns the best.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As of 2026, I am currently looking to increase my understanding in computer graphics, more specifically differential rendering. I hope to work on a lab regarding to this topic and actually do research instead of writing C++/OpenGL games.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Small bio&lt;/strong&gt;: During 2025, I interned under Zeynel Uluşan, focusing on the topic of neural formal theorem proving where we leveraged symbolic languages and novel tree search techniques to enhance the mathematical reasoning capabilities of LLMs. Moreover, during my high school years, I worked under the guidance of Asst. Prof. Gözde Gül Şahin in order to represent Türkiye in EUCYS and ISEF. In that project, I proposed a 2D tokenization technique for symbolic music representation, a custom transformer model and an evaluation metric to assess the playability of the generations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Apart from my academic life, I am a classical guitarist for the past I-have-no-idea-how-much-years, and also like to compose stuff on my DAW and record my electric guitar. You may want to checkout my &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@buraksinaakbudak&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt; to give my pieces a listen.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this blog, I write about my projects, researchs, some thoughts and guides about specific stuff such as problems I&amp;rsquo;ve faced during my works. I also share my personal travel notes sometimes, although I don&amp;rsquo;t travel as much as I did during high school years.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Have a beautiful day!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
        </item><item>
            <title>Archives</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/en/page/archives/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/page/archives/</guid>
            <description></description>
        </item><item>
            <title>Search</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/en/page/search/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/page/search/</guid>
            <description></description>
        </item></channel>
</rss>
